Hey, it could do with a little
yard maintenance, don't you think?
How does one person
live in a house this big?
Let me see.
By being very rich.
That's now what I meant.
Ah, you mean morally.
Well, we've been called in
so it's likely
that whoever lived here
paid a hefty price
in the end.
There is something off here.
This place gives me the creeps.
Normally, I'd be tempted
to mock your superstition
but in this case,
I'm inclined to agree.
Ladies first.
Boss, this is Reggie Brooks
from private security.
Found the body,
called it in.
Hi. I'm Agent Lisbon with the CBI.
This is Patrick Jane.
Hi. How you doing?
Is this gonna take long?
I'd really like to get out of here.
Why don't you just walk us through
what happened this morning?
Well, I was, doing my rounds
of the neighborhood
this morning, as always
when I got a call
that said, uh
Ms. Vogelsong's doctor
wasn't getting an answer
when he tried to call her
and asked me to follow up.
Do you know
the name of the doctor?
No, I don't.
you can call dispatch.
Okay. So the doctor told you
to go and check on her.
"I... I noticed the smell right away."
"And I, followed it
to the library"
"and... that's when
I called it in."
The final remains of Elise Vogelsong
Sacramento's tragic heiress.
You know the story, right?
You know, orphan at 12,
widow at 18.
Divorced 5 times
before she turned 40.
My mother ate that stuff up
when I was a kid.
Never heard of her.
Check out this place.
What a creep show.
And, look at this body.
I mean, it's reduced
entirely to ash.
You know, there've been a handful
of cases I've read about.
I've never actually seen it.
Spontaneous combustion,
they like to call it.
It's in a book somewhere.
"Bleak House." Dickens.
Yeah, Mr. Krook, the rag and bone man
burst into flames in his parlor.
It's not believable.
I didn't buy it, either.
Oh, um, it's...
It's a misnomer.
You know, it's not actually
spontaneous combustion at all.
Uh, it almost always happens
with a heavy drinker and a smoker.
They pass out with a cigarette
in their hand
ember falls onto clothing,
starts to burn
and smoldering cloth
acts like a wick
and it turns the victim
into a human candle
with the body's subcutaneous fat deposits
as a perfect form of tallow.
A human candle?
Isn't that awful?
Yeah, what's produced is a slow
and all-consuming burn
so in the end,
there's nothing left but ash.
So this could be
an accidental death?
Yeah. Very likely.
You notice how weird the light is?
Kind of waxy and brown?
That's because human fat is congealed
on all the light bulbs. I mean...
All right. Don't say another word,
please, okay?
This was murder
which is ironic, considering
Ms. Vogelsong's appreciation
and love of murder mysteries.
- Murder?
- Yes.
There's globules of glass
in the fireplace
and, this scotch
was opened very recently.
And that's a lot of scotch
for one woman.
There were at some point
four glasses right here
but now there are only three in the room.
Where is the fourth glass?
So two people are sitting down
relaxing, having a drink
now one of them is dead.
The other one tried to conceal
his or her presence
by throwing the fourth glass
into the fireplace. Murder.
Oh, you think?
Who's the other person, huh?
Why'd they kill her?
Well, you know,
if you hadn't mentioned
the congealed human fat
in the light bulbs
I may have had the stomach
to stick around and find out but I-I...
You're a ghoul.
Oh, thanks.
You know, my mom kept
a scrapbook of Elise Vogelsong.
You'd have thought she was family
the way she talked about her.
Your mom like that?
Nope.
I think for mom, it was a way
of feeling better about things
with my dad, you know?
No matter how bad
things got between them
it was always worse
for Elise Vogelsong.
I think that was it, anyway.
Have we got a name yet,
for the doctor who called?
Dispatcher didn't write it down.
He doesn't even know
if he got it or not.
Now this says someone poured
accelerant on Ms. Vogelsong
and lit a match, right?
Right. Best arson teams in the world
would have missed it 99 times
out of 100.
If Jane hadn't been so sure,
I'd have missed it, too.
Spectrometer says traces
of ethyl alcohol and methanol.
I'm guessing Sterno as an accelerant.
Wouldn't take much.
That's nice work.
Yeah, next of kin didn't seem
to believe it, though.
Give it time. Lisbon and Jane
will convince them.
Can you think of anybody who may
have wanted to harm your aunt?
She was an old lady
who devoted herself to charity
and helping veterans.
Who'd want to hurt her?
She was losing her mind
at the end.
Have you taken that into account?
Losing her mind how?
All right, you know what my aunt
endured in her life?
The scandals, the tragedies?
Yes. I'm sorry.
Well, she was a strong woman,
despite it all
- until about two years ago.
- And what happened?
She stopped wanting to leave the house
started getting paranoid
thought people were out to get her.
Were they?
No. Not at all.
It was all in her head.
She fired all her servants
and was living in
that big old pile by herself.
Look, the police said
that there was nothing stolen
from the house.
There are no signs of robbery.
Someone commits a murder
in a house like that
and doesn't take anything?
No money, no jewels?
No expensive works of art?
- It doesn't make any sense, does it?
- Well, not yet.
It's an ongoing investigation.
Yeah, it's ongoing.
Uh, could you provide us
with your aunt's doctor's name?
The one who called the security guard?
No, I didn't know her doctor.
I'm sorry.
As I said, my aunt had become
withdrawn in recent years.
- I didn't communicate with her much.
- You had a falling out?
No. As her mind went, she became difficult.
I admit I distanced myself.
I preferred to remember her
as she was.
Okay. So before that,
you... you were close?
Well, some of my fondest memories
from childhood
were sailing with my aunt Elise
on the "Songbird."
Your aunt liked sailboats?
Well, aside from the family's
charitable foundations
it was her greatest joy.
I don't think a week went by
that she wasn't out on the water.
Even at her age?
Was that safe?
There was a girl went with her
down at the marina.
Cayce Robbins?
That's right.
I'm Agent Lisbon
with the CBI.
This is my associate,
Patrick Jane.
We spoke on the phone.
Oh, about Elise.
You going somewhere?
Yeah, Elise always said
she wanted her ashes
scattered out at sea,
out of sight of land.
So I figured it's my duty
to make that happen.
I'm just waiting
to get the ashes.
That's gonna have to wait
until after our investigation. I'm sorry.
It's awful to think
what happened to her.
Can you think of anybody
who may have wanted to kill her?
I can't, but I only sailed with her.
I don't know much
about her life on land.
What about her mental state?
In the last few years,
you see any signs of senility?
Elise? No, she was sharper
than most people my age.
I didn't like all the pills
she was taking, though.
Doctors prescribe too many pills
these days, I think.
What were the pills
she was taking?
Or... or better still
you know the name of the doctor
that prescribed them?
You know, there's some in the cabin.
I can go get 'em.
Thank you. Very helpful.
Seems like a civilized way to travel,
don't you think?
Are you kidding?
Stuck on that thing
in the middle of the ocean?
It's like being in a prison cell
with a chance of drowning.
There you go.
Hope that helps.
"Dr. Reinhardt".
- Yeah, thank you.
- It does. Thank you.
Yeah.
Right this way, Agent Lisbon.
Come on.
I was just about to learn
how to drive her wild.
Five easy steps.
I've been Elise Vogelsong's
personal physician
for almost two years.
I felt a particular concern.
- She was in the early stages of Dementia.
- Why would you say that?
Anyone who spent any time
with Elise Vogelsong
would recognize the symptoms.
As a doctor, it was obvious.
What kind of symptoms?
Well, the onset of dementia
can manifest in various ways.
In her case, it took the form
of an intense persecution mania.
I was not comfortable
with her living alone
but... Elise Vogelsong
was a very...
Strong-willed woman.
Is that why you were so quick
to send the security company
to go and check on her?
Well, I'd spoken to Elise
the evening before
so when I couldn't get a reply
the next morning I became concerned.
I worried she'd fallen
and hurt herself.
The idea that she'd
been brutally murdered...
it's beyond all comprehension.
Well, better than the discovery
that her death was related to your care.
That must have been a relief.
Excuse me?
Well, your primary emotion
as you talk right now
about Elise Vogelsong
is that of relief.
Why is that?
Where do you...
Get this idea?
Is this an effective method of investigation
making things up?
Or do you consider evidence as well?
Somebody told us they thought
you were prescribing Elise
way too many drugs.
This...
is a mild sleep aid.
I was attempting to regulate
Elise Vogelsong's sleep cycles.
Balanced sleep cycles
are a bulwark against Dementia.
This is widely known.
Now I understand you must pursue
all avenues of inquiry
but embracing the medical
theories of laypersons...
Does not seem productive.
Did you approve
of Elise Vogelsong sailing?
I did not. Not at her age
and her condition.
But as I said,
she was a willful woman.
You didn't think it was good for her
to get out of the house?
Of course I did,
but not by going out to sea
or spending time with mentally
unstable war veterans.
That was her charity work?
The Vogelsong soldiers' home.
I told her it was dangerous, but...
Curtis and Alex Wiley.
Both artists.
They own the California
Impressionist Gallery.
Successful?
More enthusiastic than talented
from what I could gather.
They're well-liked
in the community.
So family money
keeps the business running?
- Any trouble with the police?
- None.
That's Cayce Robbins, 28.
Originally from
New London, Connecticut.
Been working on or around boats
at the Bodega Bay marina
for the last six years.
And the only thing in her file
is some unpaid parking tickets.
- What about the doctor?
- Dr. Lance Reinhardt.
Born in D.C., educated
in the U.S. and Europe.
Impressive list of honorary degrees
from prestigious universities
across the globe.
Moved to California
about five years ago.
Clean record in the state.
See what else you can find out
about Reinhardt.
See what he was doing
before he moved to California
and keep me posted.
I'm gonna go talk to the guy who runs
the Vogelsong soldiers' home.
Elise Vogelsong was a wonderful,
wonderful woman.
We've been praying for her
and for whoever it was
that committed the horrible act.
This place looks like
it has an interesting history.
The Vogelsong fortune was made
by Elise's grandfather Ernst
during the world wars.
Munitions.
This foundation was created
to ease his conscience?
Yes.
And God bless him if it did.
Elise says it gave
a purpose to her life
a purpose that was missing
for many of her relations.
Please, follow me.
Chaplain Griffin
do you know anybody who may
have wanted to do her harm
- or had a grudge against her?
- Here? No.
As I say,
she was a lifesaver.
Last year, the... the heating unit
in the building went kaput
she replaced the entire thing,
no questions asked.
How was Elise Vogelsong's relationship
with the veterans?
Oh, she was generous with
her time as well as her money.
With a certain reserve, of course.
But I did notice a bond forming between her
and one of the W.A.C.s.
- Really? Which one?
- Lissie Calhoun.
- She was a nurse in Vietnam.
- Do you think we can talk to her?
Yeah. I mean, she's usually here
in the afternoons.
I could tell her to contact you.
- We'd appreciate that.
- Of course.
I don't know what we'll do now
that Elise is gone.
I mean, there's
no one to protect us.
- To protect you from what?
- The rest of the family.
The Vogelsong fortune breeds
great entitlement and great guilt
Elise used to tell me.
And according to her
it had driven all of her
relations completely mad.
All they did was fight
with each other over the money.
Well, where does the money come from
that funds the soldiers' home?
The Vogelsong Foundation
which Elise was in charge of.
I mean, with her gone, I just...
I fear we might be shut down.
Is that a real danger?
Oh, yes. Sadly, yes.
One of the relatives was
determined to destroy us
and... and all of our work here.
According to Elise,
it was an obsession of his
to crush her and take everything
that was hers.
- Do you know which relative?
- It was a nephew. His name is Curtis Wiley.
Vogelsong legal disputes.
Wanna help?
- Rigsby.
- What?
Somebody die?
No. It's from Van Pelt.
She's learning cross drive analysis
and anomaly detection.
- And that makes you sad?
- I'm not sad.
Yeah, okay, I'm sad.
Every time she's been away in the past
and she sent a postcard
she always addressed it to me
or, you know, Wayne and the gang.
This is just addressed to "the bullpen"
like I'm nobody.
Right. She's moved on.
Yes, thank you. I know that.
Like years ago.
Well, years makes it
sound like decades.
It hasn't been that long.
You're losing your mind.
How long has it been since you've
had relations with a woman?
- Recently.
- Lying again. Find a woman.
Yeah, you know what?
You're right.
I will. It's what I have to do.
"Bullpen."
Not even an "x-o" at the end.
Move on, Wayne.
Move on.
Hey, Cho,
what do you got?
There's about 30 descendants
of Ernst Vogelsong
and every one of them seems to be
contesting a part of the will
or accusing the others of some
improper financial behavior.
Did you find out what was going on
between Elise Vogelsong and her nephew?
It was about a codicil giving Curtis Wiley
another chunk of inheritance
and a seat on the foundation board.
There's pages of claims
and counter claims
centered on whether it took
effect at 35 or 40.
Seriously?
These people
are a law firm's dream.
No kidding.
And more recently, Curtis had been
making claims of managerial incompetence.
Said that there were
accounting irregularities
at the foundation
and the soldiers' home.
Any idea the status of the case,
which way it was leaning?
No, but I've got a call out
to the probate judge.
And one thing's clear...
this much paper means bad feelings
on both sides.
This is a family matter.
It's not something that outsiders
can understand.
I understand
that you lied to us earlier.
You and your aunt
hated each other.
And you're greedy.
No, you're wrong!
That's not true.
I never felt any ill will
towards my aunt.
I loved her.
I wanted to help her.
By suing her?
Interesting way
of showing your love.
All right, look, from a financial point
of view something had to be done.
My aunt was not making good decisions.
Her mind was going.
Well, so you say, and Dr. Reinhardt
but Elise's sailing companion
didn't say so.
Excuse me if I don't put much trust
in what Cayce Robbins says.
A reading of my aunt's will
showed that little thief
manipulated my aunt
into giving her the "Songbird."
Why shouldn't your aunt
give Cayce the boat
if that's what she wanted?
Because that boat is worth
a quarter of a million dollars!
Look. All assets of any unmarried heirs
revert back to the family trust.
That's how it's done,
as my aunt well knew.
Apparently, that's not
what she wanted.
Well, she was not
in her right mind
and people were taking
advantage of that.
The expenditures of the soldiers' home
were astronomical.
One of the trustees told me.
And now we're losing
the "Songbird"?
Honey, this couple's interested
in one of your paintings.
Do you think you could
come over and talk to them?
My family's being robbed blind.
It's my fiduciary responsibility to act.
$250,000 is a lot of money.
We should go talk
to Cayce Robbins again.
I'm always happy
to take a trip to the ocean.
Well, we could
get on board and wait.
Not without a warrant, we're not.
Rules are just so...
tiresome and boring.
Ms. Robbins, hi.
We're sorry
to bother you this late.
No, please, call me Cayce.
I hope I didn't make
you guys wait too long.
I was just doing
a favor for a friend.
We just had some questions.
We talked to Curtis Wiley.
I bet he had a lot to say.
- Yeah, he's very upset.
- He's very upset?
Look, I-I didn't
expect anything
and I'm honored that Elise even
wanted to give me "Songbird"
but changing the will
affects the foundation.
- What do you mean, changing the will?
- You don't know?
I-I just got a call from the lawyers
and the doctor said Elise
was non compos mentis.
The will isn't valid.
And that affects the foundation?
Well, Elise left her seat
on the foundation board
to the chaplain
of the soldiers' home.
That goes, too,
with the will thrown out.
That's interesting.
Thank you for your time.
Look, she wasn't crazy,
you know.
It was just those pills
that doctor had her on.
That's what made her like that.
They were actually
just a mild sleeping aid.
We checked.
Well, there was more
than just those pills.
A lot more.
I thought you understood that.
All right. What have you got for me
on Reinhardt?
Well, it looks like Elise's sailing friend
might have had it right.
Took some digging.
Negligent homicide?
Where's this from?
Monaco.
You see why
the charge was brought?
Overprescribing
a pain medication.
Bingo.
It was treated as a terrible
mistake at the time
and the charges
were eventually dropped.
Still, it's not something
that would inspire confidence
in Reinhardt's patients.
Yeah, which is probably why
a great deal of effort's
been made to cover it all up.
Uh, what about the records
for what he was prescribing for Elise?
Trying to get a hold of them.
We may need a warrant.
Talk to Reinhardt.
See how he reacts
when you confront him.
Sure. Should I take Cho?
- I sent him to the soldiers' home.
- Okay.
- You must be Agent Cho with the CBI?
- That's right.
Like I told Agent Lisbon on the phone
I don't want to get anyone in trouble
but I think those two have been
plotting this for some time.
Wait. Slow down.
Who was plotting what?
The nephew and that doctor.
I mean, I didn't realize it
at the time
but I think they've been
working together for a while.
And what makes you
say that?
Uh, about a week ago,
they came in to talk to Elise.
They must have been talking about
the future of soldiers' home.
- You sure about that?
- Okay. Here's what I saw...
Elise was outside talking
with Lissie Calhoun
when Wiley
and Reinhardt appeared.
The... the conversation
got very heated.
Now Lissie Calhoun...
she's the nurse, served in Vietnam?
Yeah. I know Agent Lisbon
wanted to talk to her
but she hasn't been in
for the last few days.
Do you have her address?
Yeah. I think I do.
Follow me.
Lisbon, I'm sorry
but I think we might have to get back
to the crime scene.
Really? That place was so creepy.
Yes. But I-I'm worried
we might have missed something
because of that.
Okay, fine, but no jumping out and yelling
"boo" at me or anything like that.
I mean, seriously,
what do you take me for?
I am not going to answer that
because I'm a nice person.
"She paid through the month"
"but said she was going
to visit a friend."
- Did she say where?
- No, she didn't.
What'd she do this time?
Told her any more of it,
I'd throw her out.
Three strikes.
That's my rule.
She hasn't done anything.
I just wanna talk to her.
Well, don't get me wrong.
You know, Lissie's good people.
But she's got impulse control issues
and problems with anger management.
Think maybe she saw stuff
over in Vietnam
that nobody should see,
you know?
Yeah, I know.
Plus she drinks.
That's probably
where she is now.
So you think the friend
she's visiting is made up?
All I know is, I told her
she can't stay here if she's not sober.
I can't put up with that.
She may have been America's tragic heiress
but she sure knew how to throw a party.
Look at these photos...
hot and cold running servants,
fine food, champagne and wine.
That must have been
something to see.
She went crazy I guess?
- Lisbon?
- What?
Come take a look at this.
Look at this shelf.
Tell me what you see.
A picture frame, a silver candlestick
an old lace doily.
One lace doily.
The other doily's missing?
Yes. Now look at this.
On this shelf,
what is it...
That you don't see?
Well, that medal's gone.
I knew we missed something.
Okay, will do, boss.
Jane thinks some kind
of small commemorative object
was stolen
from the Vogelsong house.
Huh?
Never mind.
So you're still on
that computer dating site, huh?
Yeah.
It's really cool.
You can customize the kind
of woman you wanna meet.
Have you actually made
any dates
or are you just hesitating
and second-guessing yourself
like you usually do?
Yeah, I've made dates...
several. So there.
Glad to hear it.
But maybe you can also help
around the office a little bit.
Meaning?
Isn't that the Reinhardt warrant
on your desk?
No, I've been waiting
on the Reinhardt warrant for...
Oh, crap!
Dr. Reinhardt will see you
as soon as he can.
You understand I'm an officer of the law
investigating a murder case?
The doctor is with a patient
right now.
But as soon as he's done...
Hey!
Get away from the machine.
It's not what you think.
I didn't do anything.
Phenobarbital...
Clonazepam...
Diazepam...
Thorazine.
Looks to me like you did quite a lot.
Hands behind your back.
You're under arrest.
Hey, I think I found
your missing object.
Oh, yeah?
It's called the Vogelsong Medal.
And apparently,
it's kind of a big deal.
That's from Channel 7 news
a few years ago.
"Elise Vogelsong
welcomes foreign dignitaries"
"to the annual
Vogelsong Foundation dinner"
"wearing the renowned
and priceless Vogelsong Medal."
Priceless, huh?
That explains why somebody stole it.
Except that it's only priceless
when it's the Vogelsong medal.
What does that mean?
Well, melt it down,
it's worth almost nothing
but keep it as the Vogelsong Medal
you can't sell it.
So with all the treasures
in that house, why take that?
Beats me.
What about Dr. Reinhardt?
Did you talk to him?
I'm about to. With the amount
that he was prescribing her
it's no wonder people thought
she was losing her mind.
I'm amazed
she could stay upright.
Okay, I did not want
to prescribe her those pills.
She made me do it.
She blackmailed me.
Okay, you can take a seat.
So an old lady with rapidly
progressing dementia...
you gonna say that she was
the bad guy in this situation?
It's true.
I don't know how she found out
about my past, but she did.
And she said she'd tell everybody
unless I did what she said.
I just want to help people.
I'm... I'm a good doctor.
She would have ruined
my career.
She was a cruel
and vindictive woman
willing to do anything
just... to get her way.
So you weren't conspiring
with Curtis Wiley
to undo Elise Vogelsong's will?
What? No.
But you and Wiley did have
a conversation with Elise
outside the soldiers' home,
did you not?
Elise asked me
to meet her there.
That was the first and only time
I ever met Curtis Wiley
I swear on my mother's grave.
I voided that will because
I believe Elise Vogelsong
not to be in her right mind.
That's the only reason.
I tracked down
Lissie Calhoun in Vegas.
She used a credit card yesterday
to get a room.
Should I send somebody out
to go get her?
Pass it on to the locals.
Have them drop in see what she has to say.
Will do.
Oh, and I got some intel
on the lawsuit
from one of the clerks
in the probate office.
Why can't we get a judge
on the phone?
Oh, he's stuck
in some mediation thing.
Stay on the judge.
What did the clerk say?
Basically, trusts and estates
law is pretty arcane stuff
but the clerk was pretty certain
that Elise Vogelsong was gonna win.
Okay. I wanna get a warrant
to search Curtis Wiley's home
and place of business.
- I wanna lean on him hard.
- You got it.
Hello, agents.
Uh, Curtis is painting out back.
Should I go get him?
That won't be necessary.
This is a warrant
to search your business.
Could you step aside
from the desk, please?
What?
Step away from the desk, please.
Curtis, the police are here.
We've already searched your home.
This won't take long.
- My husband will put a stop to this.
- No, he won't.
What's going on here?
This is a warrant that
was issued by a judge.
It authorizes me to search
your business, your vehicle
and your persons.
I don't understand.
Why are you doing this?
Where were you the night
of the murder?
I was here at the gallery
going over paperwork.
- Alone?
- No.
No, I was here, too.
W-we were both here together.
I think you're lying.
"Hey, boss, I found something."
Hey. Those are
my personal art supplies.
There's... there's nothing
back there that you need.
Really?
This is an art supply?
My great-grandfather's medal.
Where did you get that?
Back there. It was wrapped in this.
Smells like Sterno.
No.
I'm arresting you for
the murder of Elise Vogelsong.
What...
Your client was locked
in a bitter legal dispute
with the victim over
an extended period of time.
Realizing that he had little
or no chance of winning the suit
he set about trying
to get rid of her.
Oh, this is ridiculous.
This...
You found an ally in the form
of Dr. Lance Reinhardt
and together, they started
drugging Elise Vogelsong
in carefully calibrated doses
so that the world around her
would believe that
she was going mad.
I met the man once. Once.
The murder would look to the world
like a terrible accident.
Just another in a line
of tragedies that Elise Vogelsong
had suffered in her life
and Curtis would inherit everything.
This is slanderous.
What he's saying is slander, isn't it?
Curtis, please.
It's all very neat, but it is completely
circumstantial.
You presented nothing but innuendo
and scurrilous gossip.
Except for the fact
that your client
couldn't resist taking
something from the victim...
something that represented everything
she stood for as a Vogelsong.
- The Vogelsong Medal.
- No...
Which he wrapped in a doily
taken from the house.
And that doily still has traces of the Sterno
he used to light his aunt on fire.
Now... it's just a matter
of which one is quickest
to make a deal
and testify against the other.
I'm quite sure that Dr. Reinhardt
is signing a plea deal right now
but if your client's clever enough
he might be able to save his own neck
and just serve life without parole.
Deal.
I'm innocent. No.
That was planted on me by you
for all I know. I'm innocent.
Well, it's your choice.
Don't move
and don't say a word.
Agent, please.
Give me a minute.
I'm sure I can talk sense into him.
- Don't take the deal off the table.
- Sure. Talk to your client.
They're gonna turn on each other.
It is gonna be an open and shut case
by the time we get it before a judge.
It all fits.
I'll give you that.
Yeah.
Yeah. A psychological motive
for stealing the medal
is particularly compelling.
But there's something about it
that's not right.
What do you mean?
We've got a killer.
We've got motive,
and we got conclusive evidence.
- What more do you need?
- I don't know yet.
Oh, you're just being contrary.
No, I-I swear I'm not.
Hey, Cho.
Hey, boss. Just talked to the probate judge.
He finally got in touch.
Really? What'd he say?
Well, he said that in discovery
widespread malfeasance
was found in the running of the foundation.
What does that mean?
It means that Elise Vogelsong had run
through her entire inheritance
and was plundering
the coffers of the soldiers' home
to line her own pockets.
In the past few months
she nearly emptied the bank accounts.
Elise Vogelsong? The victim?
The whole matter was gonna be referred
to the district attorney's office.
Not only was the ruling going to be
a complete victory for Curtis Wiley
but Elise Vogelsong
was going to jail.
So you're telling me
that sweet old lady
that was murdered
was really a liar and a cheat?
Yeah, and soldiers' home
is bankrupt.
And Curtis Wiley murdered his aunt
for a lawsuit he was gonna win?
And if he waited a week
he would've gotten everything he wanted.
That's horrible.
And I was just gonna take her ashes
down to the boat.
Oh, so that the girl could scatter
them at sea?
That's very kind of you, Lisbon.
Well, I'm not gonna do it now.
I'm gonna have somebody call her.
She can come pick 'em up herself.
Do you mind if I do it?
I like the idea of giving
this girl some closure.
Don't tell me you've gotten
sentimental all of a sudden.
Not at all. I just think
it's the right thing to do.
I'll call you when I'm done.
Hey.
- How's the, computer dating thing going?
- Great. Yeah. Great.
I haven't met miss right yet,
but, you know
I'm out there on the prowl,
just... moving on, like we said.
That's funny.
There must be some mistake then.
There's several women out there
who say some guy's running
a scam online
where he pretends to be
a handsome CBI cop
named Wayne Rigsby
and makes dates with women
and then he doesn't show up.
It's weird, huh?
That is weird.
They're by the elevator?
- Yeah.
- Okay.
Hi, la... wow.
There's five of you.
So I can explain.
Wow. I'm... I mean,
I'm... I'm glad that they found
who killed Elise.
It's just...
It's all so sad, you know?
Maybe now Elise
can rest in peace.
Are those the ashes?
Uh, yes. I, I remember you saying
you wanted to scatter them at sea
so I brought 'em with me.
Thank you.
I really appreciate this.
I know this is what
Elise would have wanted.
Sure.
Let's go, shall we?
What are you doing?
I always wanted
to take a boat trip
and this is a particularly
nice boat, isn't it?
You... you know, I don't think
it's a very good idea.
You're very, inexperienced
- and it can get very dangerous.
- Oh, no.
It'll be absolutely fine.
Uh, you got an emergency kit here.
That's good
which reminds me,
I should take a little bit
of the old motion sickness
medication
just as a precaution.
There we go, and one of these.
Marine flare, huh?
Wow.
- Okay. You know what?
- Cool.
You ever had
to use one of these things?
- Hey! What are you doing?
- Smoke! That's hot!
Put that out!
Calm down.
Give me... oh, my God.
Oh! sorry!
Uh, mayday! Girl overboard!
Get some help!
Uh... help!
Sorry! Sorry!
Yep.
Hello? I know you're down there!
Elise Vogelsong, I presume.
And that looks like
the money you stole
from the soldiers' home.
Let's go!
I'll get the one on the water.
Who are you?
What are you doing on my boat?
My name is Patrick Jane.
He's an agent with the CBI
and you, my dear,
are under arrest.
Bon voyage.
I didn't know about the money.
I swear.
And I didn't know she was
gonna hurt anybody.
Somebody did get hurt.
Lissie Calhoun died.
She told me that her family
was trying to get her
put away in a home.
I was just trying
to protect her.
I thought I was doing
the right thing.
But you weren't Cayce
and now you're an accessory
to murder.
I'm not. I'm n... I'm not.
I-I can't be.
I would never.
You have to believe me.
You know, she was probably
planning to kill you, too?
You were never getting
off that boat.
I feel really stupid.
What am I gonna do?
Testify.
We'll make a fair deal
for you
but you have to play straight
with us, okay?
I will.
I promise.
I believe you.
So what if I took
the money?
My grandfather made it.
It was mine by right.
But Curtis wouldn't have
seen it that way, would he?
Curtis?
Nosey little brat, that one.
Ever since he was a child.
And that's why
you contested the codicil.
You didn't want Curtis
on the foundation board.
Him, judging me?
Telling me how to run my foundation
spend my money?
Would've been
unendurable.
So you hatched your plan.
You found a doctor
you could blackmail
to get the pills
you needed.
Uh, was Cayce
in on the plan?
I told her that Curtis and the rest of them
were plotting against me
that it was the only way
I could escape.
And she was already convinced
that I was the mother
she never had.
Girls like that
are so naive and foolish.
And what about
Lissie Calhoun?
Was she naive and foolish also?
That was an unfortunate necessity.
"But the woman was a tortured soul."
"What I did was an act of mercy."
"And, uh..."
"I made sure that her death
was a peaceful one."
You certainly did.
Overdosing her on barbiturates
and burning her to ash...
that is a peaceful way to go.
Then all that was left was
sending Cayce to Las Vegas
to rent a room with
the dead woman's credit card
and planting evidence
on your nephew.
Yeah.
That was rather fun.
Even if it did mean having to enter
that tacky little shop of theirs.
Curtis had been eyeing grandfather's
medals since he was a boy.
Thank you, Mr. Jane.
Thank you for saving my husband
despite your colleague's
best efforts to imprison him.
You can, thank me by forgiving
my colleague, Agent Lisbon
and keeping the old soldier's home open.
Oh, don't worry.
Soldiers' home will stay open
as long as there are
veterans who need it.
And we forgive you,
Agent Lisbon.
Thanks.
- Bye.
What?
We followed the evidence.
You... you did.
You... followed the evidence.
Okay. Okay, I was wrong.
But we followed
the evidence.
You know what gave me second thoughts
about Elise Vogelsong?
She read too many
murder mystery novels.
There you go.
That's not police work.
That's guessing.
You should try it sometime.
Now I'm gonna pursue Red John.
Ciao.